soft engineering radio episode 109
eBay's architecture principles with a
Randy shop this is software engineering
radio the podcasts for professional
developers on the web at se - radio
dotnet se radio prints irrelevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
soft engineering topics every 10 days
thanks to our audience and the partners
listed on our website for supporting the
hot rod
[Music]
so welcome listeners to a new episode of
software engineering radio this is
another episode we are recording at a
jowl derived conference this is Q Khan
and today we are talking to Randy Sharpe
from eBay so welcome Randy thank you
so Randy why don't you introduce
yourself to the audience and sure
well I'm Randy shell PI I'm a
distinguished Architect at eBay my
particular area of specialization at
eBay is the search engine so I'm
responsible for sort of all the vertical
functionality from the webpages
down to the depths of the search engine
that eBay has written itself I've been
at eBay for about three and a half years
before eBay I was the chief architect at
a small security company called
tumbleweed Communications and I worked
there for six years before that I worked
at various other places including Oracle
for a long time okay so and the topic of
today's show is well architectural
principles in obviously eBay so why
don't you give us a general broad
introduction to to what the challenge is
what what what the magnitude of the
problem is at eBay and then we can look
at how you solve that sure well I always
like to start by talking a little bit
about the magnitude of the problem
because that sort of sets the sets the
context right so at the moment eBay
manages about 250 million registered
users worldwide we have about two
billion photos so that puts us in the
realm of even a large photo sharing
sites eBay users do just over two
thousand dollars in trades every second
worldwide so they trade two thousand
dollars worth of goods every second we
do well over a billion page views a day
100 million items in 50,000 categories
worldwide we store about 2 petabytes of
data which is which is quite large how
many zeros all that that's quite a lot
of zeros ^ 12/12/12
yeah it's quadrillion so well
yeah and then we do about 5.5 billion
API calls every month no so it's it's a
decent-sized problem and it gives us as
you'll see as we talk forward it gives
us some particular challenges which we
have to solve yeah the other aspect of e
based problem or eBay's issue is the
dynamism of it it's we change the sight
constantly so every two weeks we're
rolling about a hundred thousand new
lines of code and we do a search
Federation process where every two weeks
new code appears on the site in total we
do about 300 new features every quarter
some of them small some of them large
and it's a world wide side of course so
we're in 38 countries worldwide and what
that ends up being is for the database
savvy is about 48 billion sequel
statements that we actually execute
every day so that's not one of those
metrics where more is better yeah but it
but it does give a give a sense of the
scale of the problem yeah so and from
the things you just mentioned I take it
that obviously some of the forces and
challenges in the architecture are
probably obviously scalability and maybe
an ability to evolve the system
continuously without shutting it down so
why don't you elaborate a little bit on
the core architectural forces that
you're going to address with the
patterns and practices we're going to
talk about in the main section of
interview so there are sort of four four
or five architectural forces that we
think of and you mentioned the first one
quite obviously scalability is our
primary challenge if the second is
availability so any public website is
going to care to be available to its
users and so that's one of the core the
core aspect of it
latency both latency for users in terms
of how they're how quickly the system
responds to them but then also data or
execution latency how rapidly does a
users an event driven by the user change
data that there's in our persistent
storage and have and how quickly does it
actually cause follow-on effect and then
of course for a large-scale system you
need to worry about manageability so we
need to make sure that our operations
team which the site it's simple it's
maintainable and we can diagnose
problems and then the final which is
similar to scalability but I think is
worth talking about separately is simply
cost and we measure cost in terms of hue
an effort so development effort know how
quickly can we evolve the site how
expensive as a feature or less expensive
and then also the operational cost so
the hardware the software the people to
run the site energy probably is also
absolutely that's right yes and your you
have you talked about exactly that with
a varnish mobile right and it's yes so
power consumption in our in so anybody
who runs large data centers knows this
but power consumption simply powering
and cooling the hardware is actually the
biggest limiting factor for the growth
of our hardware so it's not it's not
physical space it's not well sorry it's
not physical space it's not being able
to buy the machine it's simply being
able to power the machines and to cool
the machines and what we're finding we
in eBay but everyone else Google Yahoo
Amazon etcetera are all finding the same
thing that the size of an of an
individual data center is now exceeding
what a residential power grid and most
of the United States can power so now
you have to start thinking about more
and more and more smaller data centers
and and architecting around that so it's
actually that by the bat is actually one
of our main challenges and do--the is
exactly that yeah okay so why don't you
give us an overview about the let's say
most important strategies that you use
to solve those or address these issues
and then we can look at each of them in
detail sure well I like to think about
our approach in terms of four different
strategies the first approach is
partition everything split everything
into manageable chunks the second
strategy that we apply is be
asynchronous everywhere so try as much
as possible to move processing to an
asynchronous flow rather than a
synchronous flow the third strategy is
automation automate everything that's
possible to automate and that has and
that sort of expressed in writ small by
how how individual components are
configured they should automatically
adjust or adapt to their environment and
then also the larger scale automation of
sort of how does a system improve itself
over time and can we evolve or machine
learning our way into in doing better
and then the final strategy is remember
that everything fails so how do you
design a system that can remain
available in given of realities that
everything all the hundreds of thousands
of pieces of infrastructure will fail at
every at any given moment no okay so I
think the the rest of the interview or
discussion is going to be looking at
those in in detail and and looking at
specific examples of how these
principles and strategies strategies are
applied so let's start with obviously
the first one partition everything sure
so again the first strategy is about
partitioning everything into smaller
chunks and the way I like to think about
it or the way our head of research likes
to talk about it is if you can't split
it you can't scale it so simply scaling
with site two you know more than a
billion pages and so on is none no
single machine or single system is going
to be able to handle that load and so
vertical scalability only takes you so
far so the the way that keeps the system
simple and maintainable but yet
available and growable is to split the
system into individual chunks and I'll
talk about individual examples of how we
split that in different parts of our
infrastructure so it's pretty obvious
but why would somebody
why would somebody split their
architecture the main motivation is
scalability right it's the ability to to
hold costs constant so have a constant
size unit of processing let's say
whether it's an application server a
database or whatever but some particular
unit that's a reasonable price
performance them right and then be able
to kiss Cal horizontally by adding more
and more of those units but the other
the other aspect sort of less maybe less
obvious are availability and
manageability if you think about the
individual components as individual
components you can be maintaining or
dealing with a particular component you
could in the worst case take a
particular slice of the infrastructure
offline and manage it separately without
without affecting the availability of
the rest of the interest after or maybe
updating half of the nodes to a new
version and you know doing these things
exactly right exactly right and I can
talk more about that as we go along but
but definitely one of the main ideas is
that if you think of if you think of the
infrastructure as partitioned into
smaller sly
you can be doing rolling right updates
in parts of the infrastructure where the
other parts are staying stable so the
first aspect of partitioning that is
maybe the hardest and therefore I want
to start with first is partitioning the
data tier petition M database itself and
that's something that's becoming a lot
more well-known within the industry but
it was relatively new when we started
doing it or really when everybody like I
started doing it sort of all without
knowing about one another so I guess I
just talked a little bit about the
patterns that we employ and splitting we
have two to two patterns and we'll see
them instantiated throughout the
throughout the infrastructure but the
first is functional segmentation so
dividing things into different
functional areas so in a base example we
will have the selling systems distinct
from the buying systems distinct from
the search systems distinct from various
back-end systems and so on if we
actually have quite a few different
divisions there that's sort of
functional segmentation and then the
other pattern is something that I call
horizontal split and that's simply being
able to chop a single functional unit
into smaller and smaller pieces to be
able to manage and grow them separately
yeah but that means that you need some
kind of dispatcher if you access the
persistent store because the the actual
data you are looking for might be on
this this or that host machine database
exactly right and what I'll tell you
about that because that's one of it
that's one of the main challenges of
horizontally split by the data tier yeah
okay but but first maybe the the
slightly simpler approach still
interesting is functional segmentation
of the data tier so again as I mentioned
we segment our databases into particular
functional areas so there's a you a set
of user databases there's a set of item
databases that are about the items that
we deal with or a set of transactional
databases products account feedback and
so on transactional transactional
meaning not in the sense of database
translation if they tell like the boss
the shopping cart or something yes
transaction meaning a purchase okay some
if you we call them transactions you can
think about them as the purchase flow or
checkout that's sort of it doesn't -
make sure the term transaction in the
context of database is not misunderstood
that's right and and they do a thank you
for for pointing that out yeah so for us
that the databases that are around
trends
actions are about essentially the
relationship of users to items if you
like right a user has this user has
purchased this item and items have
multiple quantities and could be
purchased multiple times and so on so
there's too many too many thing anyway
but so so once you've decided that you
need to divide your databases into
different different functional segments
how do you do it well what's interesting
at least to me is that you can do that
the same principles that you use to
divide information into tables in a
single database is that exact same
approach that same data modeling
approach you take at one level higher
right so the user databases include not
a single table of users but a whole
suite of related tables all which are
sort of partitioned will by the user ID
if you like and similarly for items so
there's a sort of feel like a central
item table and then there's a whole
suite of other tables that are related
to that but but those but those are you
know by item as distinct for by user or
by transaction or whatever so you use
the same data data modeling techniques
that you would ordinarily use and so
what that ends up at least in the eBay
infrastructure is that we end up having
a hunt a thousand different logical
databases and we spread them over 400
different physical hosts we don't make a
one-to-one mapping between a logical
database in a physical database we have
another sort of set of indirection there
where there's a logical to physical
mapping that's functional segmentation
the next the next pattern is applied to
databases as horizontal split so
essentially that's take the user
database the overall user stop data data
set write the overall data set about
items and how do you divide it up well
it turns out that of course there are
multiple different ways of dividing the
data data up you can do something very
simple where you hash or mod on a key so
item ID or user ID if it ends in one it
goes in this database if it ends in two
it goes in that database etc and there
are there are also imagine doing range
things user user one to a million or go
in this users want to know n to 2
million going another and
and then and then there are more
complicated schemes like a lookup scheme
sort of like a imagine a routing table
something like that and then you can
combine those those schemes in different
ways this is I as I hinted before is
something that's becoming increasingly
known within the industry the industry
standard term we don't use this
internally but the industry standard
term is sharding right that's I heard
about that when I think Google published
the hive on a chart exactly right
exactly right
yeah so when we started doing this and
we've actually built something
internally which is equivalent to
hibernate shards it's we call it our own
data access layer and it does the
standard or our mapping but it also does
the sort of shard management that you
hinted at before where there's a bit of
room most of the operations are routing
operations right I need to update this
particular item so I need to go to their
appropriate database that has that some
of them we try to do this as little as
possible but some of them are kind of
scattered gather operation I used to do
stowing together to talk about these
that are expensive then those are very
expensive and I'll talk and let me let
me talk about that in a second but we
try to make sure that the scatter gather
operations are we try to minimize the
the times that we do scattered our
operations and actually try to do them
in different types of infrastructure but
but I'll but but that's but that's what
this layer is for yeah in which the
hibernate shards would would would do as
well so a sort of routing or aggregation
layer and that lives in our in our
application server tier but back to the
back to the split idea so given a
particular item ID or user ID we know
which particular host that it belongs in
and this dal this data access layer
allows us to to route to the particular
host right and of course just as
hibernate shards would it would it
abstracts the developers from knowing
about how how an item is associated with
a particular split and so on but yeah so
a bit on the sharding term that's that's
something that's that's come out of
Google but that's the term that they use
internally and then also Yahoo tends to
use that term as well so that's that's
the standard way we should be talking
about this that we is it we have shards
the corollary and this is maybe the most
controversial thing that
when I give this talk that people people
react to is that eBay doesn't use
database transactions to be more precise
eBay doesn't use any distributed
transaction rights right though we do
single-ride is of course a transaction a
single right is its own transaction and
then we do bunch together I'll talk
about this in a second we do bunch
together multiple inserts or updates
into a single right which is
transactional for that but we don't do
any client-side transactions at all and
we have a j2ee infrastructure we don't
do any client-side transactions if we do
no two-phase commit
mm-hm nothing like that so whenever we
need to do we sort of have two things
happen transactionally together like
updating a master a detail table we do
that with what we call an anonymous PL
sequel block that's an Oracle specific
term but it's essentially a little bit
of stored procedure passed along in the
call saya it's like a closure in
programming languages we're gonna take a
piece of behavior and feed it to
something else which yes sure or or if
you think about it it's a little mini
script yeah it's a it's a mini script so
okay you you go ahead the reason why
you're doing this is because you expect
that this typically doesn't fail because
it happens down in the database so it's
it's a kind of isolation that's
different from transactions or why you
do oh yeah is let me back it so let me
back up a little bit and say why we
don't use transactions oh I didn't I
didn't motivate very well the why is
simply that because we functionally
segmented the architecture into users
user data is over here and item data is
over here in transaction data is over
here and then further because we've
segmented we've partitioned or split or
shorted the user data into 10 or 20
different shards and the item data into
10 or 20 or a hundred different shards
there's no single data tip any operation
that's interesting you know the user
buying something ends up having having
effects in different places of the
interaction right so let's pretend that
well it's a real example I'm bidding on
something there's the actual bid event
or the bid update that happens in the
item database on that particular item
but then are also other systems that we
need that we need to update that or we'd
like for better or for worse to
happen at roughly the same time as that
that bit update counts and and history
for the four user activity right that
they can see in there and their Webre in
their webpages and so on so all those
things it's just impossible the way that
we've there's no single database that
holds all of them so there's no way that
we can do it in a non distributed
transaction right once once you decide
then that you have an operation that
occurs over multiple databases you have
a choice of trying to do a distributed
transaction or trying to do something
else well as Vernor phobos says very
well and other people as well the
distributed transactions are sort of a
bane of scalability it sort of grinds
the entire system to a halt yeah and so
so in terms of in terms of scaling that
that's really not an option for us
there's a whole trade-off of consistency
availability and partitioning which
people may have heard of the cap this
will called cap theorem so we need to
have partitioning for scalability we
need to have availability so what that
means is we give up on consistency
because that's the choice that's forced
on us by by the theorem essentially so
we choose a and P we lose C but we'd
like to have C sees a nice thing to have
right we'd like to have consistency so
so what we actually end up doing is in
other words how do we guarantee
consistency without doing these
distributed transactions or without
doing two-phase commit or whatever that
the the simple approach is that you can
often get consistent behavior or semi
consistent behavior by simply ordering
the database operations in the
appropriate way right you update when
you're doing an insert for example it's
a reverse of what people often think
about it but if you do an insert of
detail records before you insert the
master record you never end up with a
dangling a dangling situation right
because I can't see the details as long
as the master hasn't been exactly right
exactly right so that's one example and
there are plenty of other examples if
something you know if I want to have a
update and B update happening together I
just simply do a update and then I do B
update and then once I know that a
update has succeeded I can I can do B
update
well now the transactional issue is what
if B fails do I need to roll back a and
so on so
the the medic met a question which I'll
get back to in in a moment is do we
really need acid consistency for every
operation so I'll come back to that one
in a second but particularly for this
type of but assuming that we do need
some type of consistency there what we
do is we we typically follow along that
that update with an asynchronous event
which can go around and clean things
back up so you can do so instead of
thinking of it as the transaction
succeeded or failed think of it as I did
these operations and now I'm in this I'm
in this interim state and I need to
recover from that state yeah so the
recovery can typically happens in an
asynchronous way so we either have a
batch sort of a batch job that goes
through and cleans things up or weak you
up in a synchronous event and it's it
has guaranteed delivery it doesn't
happen immediately but it happens
eventually so that means that
potentially a user can encounter some
kind of inconsistent state because the
quote non transaction you know the
distributed thing over the several
databases didn't work and the cleanup
thing hasn't been executed yet yeah so
let me that's a that's a great point and
so it's yes theoretically possible for
something like that to happen of course
I will say I'll say several things one
is that there are many in fact most in
fact almost all of such situations where
it doesn't matter and actually can't be
noticed okay so that's the first thing
things that we really care about like
ordering of bids at the end of an
auction that stuff's that stuffs
transactionally handled it all is in a
single database so that's not a big word
it's things like well I'm selling my
item and I'm also updating my seller
preferences at the same time we make a
business decision that it is more
important for us to make sure that the
item is listed to be sold than it is to
go and at the same time transactionally
with that update go and change the
seller preferences right now so again
the meta point which I'll expand on a
little bit right now is think
consistency is not an all-or-nothing
proposition right right in the acid
database world it is the transaction
succeeded or it failed on or off binary
yeah the reality of large-scale systems
is that
the degree it's a spectrum and the
degree of trading of of consistency can
be traded off with those other metrics
and that's what the the cap theorem
tells us and Eric Brewer discovered this
ten years ago right in 1998 and it's
taken us a while for for it to be kind
of percolate through the through the
community and and everybody sort of
understand it but the point is that
there are some operations that need to
be very highly consistent and the one
hundred percent is the absolutely
appropriate number and nothing less is
nothing less but there are other cases
where in fact again the majority of
cases where it doesn't need to be
transactional at certainly at that
moment and something where an
asynchronous event that goes and
recovers is perfectly appropriate and
then there are plenty of situations a
significant percentage of Osen things
where consistency is just never it's
just not all that important right some
information is it's okay to lose some
some information because we got the we
got the stuff that was really important
and if somebody has to redo an operation
that's unfortunate and we wish it didn't
happen sure but that's the cost and the
price that we pay for having an
available system and a scalable system
I think a term that's used in this
context sometimes is also compensating
transactions that you explicitly undo
something if the overall thing didn't
work yeah and so if I could lay out the
if there's a begin the spectrum of
consistency and backing away from the
mote so there's an acid transaction 100%
consistent if okay then backing away
from that would be something like
compensating transactions backing away
from that would be a sort of best effort
a synchronous asynchronous event which
would go and clean things up and then
backing away from that would be sort of
less and less effort that we spend on
inconsistent and again just a point that
all that I'll make is architectural II
the degree of consistency is one of
those other knobs and dials that you
have to play once you reel once you
can't kind of get the Zen of being
inconsistent yeah it frees you quite a
lot to build ya systems that's that our
scale scalable and available and it
becomes yet another tool in your toolbox
how you die all consitency up or down
along that spectrum and it also and it
also fits together nicely with the
asynchronous thing that we'll talk about
later exactly right it feeds right into
the asynchronous thing yep so but first
let's look at partitioning other aspects
of the system we talked about the
database early the application tier yes
the next market rate yeah so I started
with the hard one which is partitioning
the data the much easier problem is
partitioning the application tier so we
could have implemented it in other ways
but eBay zem eBay's application tier is
a java-based
tier we run on servlets and and so it's
very it's a minimal amount of j2ee but
that's but if you want to buy B's no e
JB's nothing like that but we sort of
written our own internal infrastructure
is too strong a word but a set of pojos
essentially that do that do that kind of
do that kind of functionality for us
anyway but but for us it's some it's
easy to scale the application tier
because we make it entirely stateless
right so and I'll I'll come back to the
implicate the sort of corollary
implication of that in a moment but we
we
we first functionally segment the
applications here in the same way as we
do or similar to how we do the databases
so there's a set of application servers
that deal with a selling part of the
application a set of application that
servers that deal with the finding or
search part the buying the check out dot
dot we end up having about 200 more than
200 of those individual pools some large
some small partition by functionality
and that's partly for very good
architectural reasons that mainly why we
do it but there's also the reality that
a single EA our file can't hold the
entire eBay application so it's sort of
out of necessity that we've had to learn
to do that in any of them
so that's segmenting it functionally
again the next pattern is the horizontal
split pattern so again within the search
pool or set of search pools within the
selling pool etc all the application
servers all the hundreds or thousands of
application servers that are in that
pool are all entirely equal and each
conserve the load its load balanced in a
very standard way so there's nothing
particularly tricky about that except
that it has implications for application
design so the implication is is that we
have absolutely no session State at all
so on the server on the server so that's
how you can keep the application servers
entirely stateless and completely
horizontally scalable so it means that
we can take at any given at any moment
we can shut down and can and do shut
down say half the application servers in
a pool yeah upgrade them to a new
version of the code which we're doing
every two weeks and then do a flip or or
do rolling updates where we do 10% 50% %
zone so all that kind of stuff gives us
the ability to manage that quite
flexibly and gives the operations team
the ability to do that well that has
strong implications for the kind of
applications our application developers
can build so we don't begin we don't
store any any session State there and
the reason for that is a bit obvious
when you take a step back if the since
the eBay application if you like is
implemented on multiple distinct pools
it means that when on when a user goes
through the website that sort of session
flow it means they're going to
from a selling application to a search
application to a few item application
etc etc so no there's no one place in
the infrastructure that they're going to
keep coming back to where you could even
store the session state and and that's
actually a good discipline for us
because it forces us to to design the
application in an entirely stateless way
so how do we but Randy you say there is
there is session state there how do you
deal with it right how do you do multi
page flows and so on well there aren't
any aren't any there's nothing new Under
the Sun or there's not really any magic
it's simply using for most of the
session state we use either URL URL
rewriting or cookies cookies are limited
as everybody probably knows or will soon
discover cookies are limited by the RFC
to 4k so we only get in 4000 bytes worth
of cookie space which seems like a lot
to start but actually when that covers
everything that ebay.com does it it
starts to become pretty limiting so just
to clarify that maybe for for users I
mean using cookies is nothing special
but what you're getting at is that you
don't use a cookie to store some kind of
ID which we then use on the server to
look up a session information data which
can be anything you literally put all
this data information into the cookie
yeah the width we do yes with a few
exceptions okay so the few exceptions at
the moment are for multi page flows
where so imagine somebody is selling
selling an item that's not something you
know you can't enter all the or don't
enter all the information in a single
page but you need to we need to retain
that transient state going along so how
we do that is exactly how you hint which
is there's essentially an ID that's in
the cookie that refers to something in a
scratch database in a database yet now
so it's not in memory or even on disk in
one of the application the application
server tier it's it's physically on a
database and what that database is
limited to one of your logical database
things so it's something that's kind of
local to all of your applications yes
that's exactly right and then we're
we're experimenting with other schemes
where where we have a a session storage
that's
in a database but it's separate from the
application server tier and we're kind
of working working the working the
issues through on that but we sort of
think of those as server-side cookies
right and just like cookies the app from
the application developers perspective
the developer has to assume that that
cookie can be deleted at any time right
so really important transient state like
as for a multi page flow as I hinted
that goes in a database as I all our
important information does that doesn't
live permanently in that database that's
what I call it a scratch database but
important data lives in databases and
other transient stuff just gets passed
back and forth so that's our that's our
approach okay and then the final the
final sort of example of partitioning is
the search infrastructure and that's the
part that's near and dear to my heart
because my particular area of expertise
so our search infrastructure so the
functional segmentation is simply that
the search infrastructure is func is
read-only as you might imagine a search
infrastructure would be it's
functionally segmented from the rest of
the data sort of transactional part of
the database of the site transactional
databases of the site and I'll talk a
little bit later about how the one how
the one gets transferred to the other be
updated from x right that's a synchrony
right there so we'll talk about that as
we go forward by it but this but the
search function the search engine is a
functionally segment a functionally
different part of the site as the
transactional data so I mean that that's
something I've heard also in these data
warehousing and and data cube
applications where you prepare the data
in a way that is not suitable for
transactional because it might contain
duplicate and stuff it's not necessarily
always normalized but it is optimized
for for queries yeah that's that's a
very insightful and lt to draw the eBay
search engine is to the ebay
transactional databases as the eBay data
warehouse which also exists is to look
at it was those transactional databases
right there's to use data warehousing
terminology there's a kind of ETL
process which I'll talk about extract
transform load right which takes the
data from the probe from the primary
databases and moves it over into the
search engines it doesn't work like most
warehouse ETL processes do but but
that's a detail the general idea is yes
it's a kind of read-only it's a
different data structure right a search
engine is an inverted index it's a
difference a very entirely different
data structure and should be from third
normal form style relational database is
it a relational database or is it really
different it is very different okay it's
it's it's a search engine like Google or
Yahoo developed by the same people that
develop the Alta Vista search engine and
as with many search engines it's
developed on similar principles which is
that it's an inverted index there's a
set of documents with IDs keywords are
indexed into those documents and query
operations happen by intersecting lists
of vectors of of those keywords very
sound very simply and there's a lot of
there's a lot more detail about about
how that works
the challenge for just as an aside the
challenge for that eBay style search
engine is that our users expect the
search engine to be updated in
essentially near real-time right when
somebody bids on an item that changes
the price and price is a filter that
people are very interested in querying
on so it actually means that the style
the sort of classic web search engine
style of you build the index in a kind
of batch mode and then upload it to the
to the search engines is something that
doesn't really work for us it needs to
be a lot more real-time so I'll talk a
little bit about how that real-time
system works in my asynchrony section
but anyhow the the but the sort of to
finish the thought on scalability for
search the idea is that the search
engine can be horizontally split so
there's this overall search index of
whatever size it is we divide it up into
chunks of 10 or 20 or 60 or 100 and then
divide the infrastructure that way and
then we have an aggregator piece which
now does do scatter gather over all
those different parts of the of the
index
so somebody queries for iPod or Mickey
Mouse or Wii and the aggregator sends
the query to each one of the different
splits or shards and gets the results
back and aggregates and send somebody
user so
okay so that was the discussion on
partitioning the next of your basic
architectural strategies is or boss or
whatever is to be asynchronous
everywhere this is something we all know
but as the systems grow larger and
larger becomes more and more important
that the more processing that you can do
asynchronously the better there are
obvious reasons for that scalability is
one where component if component a and
component B are linked asynchronously
you can scale a and B separate from one
another right availability is maybe
another another key point which is that
a and B will not necessarily always be
up at the same time so you want to have
the ability to have a be available and B
not be available and some kind of
asynchronous queue or topic or some kind
of way of asynchronously
linking those two things allows you to
do that so a can be up and print can
perform its job without B being up at
that moment the slightly more subtle
point is that not only this the up down
state of B and a are decoupled but also
what we call availability
characteristics so when we build out a
particular pool or piece of
infrastructure one of the very first
things we ask is does it need to be
so-called always available does it need
to be highly available which isn't
always does it need to be sort of
best-effort available etc etc again like
consistency or anything else it's a sort
of spectrum of availability right and
it's more expensive to do the more more
available so you can decouple the
availability characteristics of the two
things maybe a doesn't need to be always
available but B doesn't need to be right
as long as they're linked asynchronously
and then of course latency you can
improve user experience latency by
getting back to the user very quickly
doing some of the more expensive
processing later at the very explicit
cost though of the data or execution
latency happens later because that's an
asynchronous process and then then the
other sort of maybe more subtle point
but I think should be appreciated more
than it is is that when there's a
synchronous integration between
components the cost
metric is a little bit different you
don't have to build out for the peak
load if there's there's a queue there
you don't build you don't need to build
for the peak load you simply need to
build for the average load right or
maybe the above average load but in any
event because as you hit your peak the
instead of it's sort of the queue allows
you to spread the processing out over
time yeah the queue cools it up Pacific
use it and flat and strengthens it
exactly it's exactly dampening in e it
it takes it takes high amplitude
fluctuations that peaks and valleys are
and turns them flatter right so that
helps quite a lot so patterns that we
apply asynchronously are sort of well
known patterns in the industry one is
sort of message dispatch right and
event-driven or message driven model and
the other is something that I call
periodic batch which should be familiar
to everybody that the eldest eldest of
us will be under that as well well no
I'm the older one of the two of us
that's for sure but in any event people
who've been around for a while we're
familiar with a batch yes so some
particular examples of those patterns
and the eBay infrastructure are
something that we call event streams so
in very sort of JMS style approach you
know when things happen on eBay there
are lots of different systems that are
interested in nothing having happened
right so somebody has listed an item
somebody has purchased an item
somebody's bid on an item all those
things are interesting events that other
people are interested in knowing about
it and doing stuff with and so we've
developed as is I want our own
infrastructure if we're doing that but
it's very much along the GMs style lines
so typically what happens is a print the
primary use case that lists an item or
bids an item or whatever also as part of
its insert or update of that record also
is inserting an item into an event table
and that event gets consumed by these
multiple consumers that run
asynchronously so that's again where we
use this trick of plc of anonymous plc
blocks and making that transactional
right yeah so the so it's a single
database transaction to update the
current items current price with the bed
and insert
and cue the event the sort of item that
did event for other people to process so
and where do those cue tables live I
mean they are part of one of those
systems otherwise you couldn't do it
with your anonymous SQL block yes that
means that some other system needs to
watch this table of the other system so
you have these dependencies between
those systems in the sense that they
monitor each other's cue tables or even
tables it's that's exactly right so in
order as you could I mean very
insightful as you correctly point out in
order for us to do it at a single
database transaction by its very nature
the cue table or really the the segment
of the cue table or the shard of the cue
that lives that is associated with these
particular set of items or these
particular set of uses or whatever needs
to live in the same be co-located in the
same database as the item table or the
user table or whatever absolutely true
but that actually has advantages not
disadvantages if you think about it for
a second because the it means that the
primary data and the event data are
co-located in a single split yes for a
single shard so yes when a consumer is
interested in consuming events out of
that particular shard they are they do
have a dependency on that database but
they already did in some sense because
they have a dependency to read the cue
write but they also have a dependency I
mean typically they have the dependency
to read the data as well yeah so it so
it it works out quite well actually sort
of a very natural way of essentially
partitioning events along the same lines
as partitioning the data yeah so the
asynchrony there is again a very
standard JMS model there are multiple
consumers each of which are consuming
those events and the key sort of design
thing that we've been able to take
advantage of is the design principle for
the events rooms we built or simply that
we don't care about exactly once
delivery and we don't care about order
this has implications for our
application developers but it's again
just like trading off consistency it
frees up the ability to do a much more
performance system so we talked about
using asynchronous message message
dispatch to communicate between the
different separated applications and
charts of those applications
the async metaphor or principle play
with the search infrastructure in the
updating of the index we talked about
before so we use exactly the same
pattern although as you'll see the
implementation of that pattern is
slightly different but fundamentally the
idea is that again interesting things
happen in the primary databases people
list items they bid on items items are
purchased and so on and we want those
those changes to be reflected and
searched as quickly as possible right so
how we do that is we have a sort of
asynchronous feeder infrastructure we
call it simply feeding updates that
happen
on the primary databases into the search
infrastructure so how that works is we
have something for each of the sort of
shards of item database let's say we
have a sort of search feed or
application which is a sort of demon
which is periodically polling for
updates that happen on the primary
databases what happens is that that
feeder application notices the updates
persists those updates locally for a
reason I'll tell you but talk about in a
second then messages those updates out
over a multicast message bus and the
individual nodes of the search
infrastructure are all listening are
listening each listening to appropriate
set of those messages to update
themselves so the reason why there's
this intermediate persistence is that
the multicast bus is multicast messaging
is of course unreliable so but we'd like
it to be reliable or semi reliable so
the way we make it reliable is that when
nodes notice that they've missed a
message they send a message back to the
the search feed or application which
saying hey I missed message for or
missed message five
could you please resend that to me and
how does it know how to resend it it
reads it from the persistent storage
right right okay so so that's the sort
of a asynchrony part and then those
individual nodes are again listening to
those messages and they keep their their
slice of the search index in memory and
they update that search index in memory
and then it's immediately available to
be queried so okay you already talked
about the batch stuff before
that sounds really old style but it's a
good way of obviously batching things
that that happened only at certain time
intervals so they want to talk about
that a little bit
sure I'll talk briefly about that and
you say exactly what you say is exactly
correct that the the batch is a sort of
old-style 1970s transaction processing
approach but it's still a very good one
not everything is appropriate for
messaging so it's typically appropriate
for those things that are scheduled or
infrequent or frankly particularly
expensive such things that we do once an
hour once a day once a week things that
we don't need to do very often you know
those are those are types of things that
are perfectly appropriate for batches so
that allows us to do large summations
over over large amounts of data but
actually also we kind of we end up
combining the two patterns as well so
we'll have a batch that reads a bunch of
primary data and then generates a bunch
of downstream processing through message
dispatch so we'll have a batch that
collects collects a bunch of data and
then it generates a whole series of
other events that can be consumed later
on so the two patterns are quite
complementary to one another right
anything else
on I think that's about all I have to
say so strategy number three automate
everything automate everything so again
it's pretty obvious but as the as the
number of systems and the complexity of
systems grows it becomes more and more
difficult to manage it manually I mean
that's true of hardware that's also true
of software so if we as software
engineers can build systems that can be
more automatable right and adapt
themselves to their environment that
makes it much easier to manage and also
has a bunch of other nice effects as
well so clearly there's a there's a
scalability effect for your organization
you scale number of machines without
linearly scaling the number of humans
yeah machines are less expensive so
there's a cost advantage but again maybe
the less less a more subtle and less
appreciated one is you can do different
kinds of functionality more
sophisticated kinds of functionality in
an adaptive or automated system then
typically you can wear with manual
tuning right if I'm tuning a thread pool
the size of a thread pool from
nine to ten to twelve as a human I only
have so much attention that I'm gonna
put to that yeah and I need to sleep and
I think but but something where that
that could be configured in an adaptive
way and the machine could tune itself
freeze the human to do something else
even something something very simple
like that oh it's also something Bob
henro talked about in the
fault-tolerance episodes that you should
make humans aware of what's going on but
you should take them out of the critical
path of actually adapting or recovering
a system that's a very nicely nice way
to say it yeah yeah yeah
so so basically you have a bunch of
metrics that you measure all the time
and then you have a rule set of rules
and they tune the system itself sort of
that's that's a general idea or further
cases where we've been where we've done
this that's the general idea so one
specific example is again with a sort of
event streaming system the individual
consumers we said it we said it we call
it what you call an SLA a service level
agreement for a particular consumer
saying something like you know you
consumer need to have processed 99% of
the events within one minute or 10
seconds or whatever and then given that
SLA the the consumer then Tunes its
various parameters to meet that SLA with
minimum resources right so if load is
high it might use more consumer
instances pull more often more threads
etc when when the load is lower it might
dial that back but but that's been very
very effective and helpful for us in
that way so the other more maybe
sophisticated approach is sort of less
about adaptive adaptively configuring
and more about machine learning okay so
this is something that I've been working
on for the last while and which is what
you might call the adaptive finding
experience at eBay so how can we adapt
the search experience which is one of
the main experience that people have at
eBay how can we adapt it to the
particular context that the user is in
right how can we learn from what that
user or that type of user has done in
the past what can we learn about what
the people who have searched for iPod
their Mickey Mouse or whatever
have done in the past how can we add
dynamically adapt the experience in that
way so as with any machine learning
setup you need a feedback loop so that
feedback loop for us is a couple of
obvious steps we collect data about what
has actually what we've shown and what's
actually happened afterward we sort of
aggregate that data correlate it
together in the in a sort of in the
background then we make some inferences
from that we deploy those inferences or
those rules or those metrics back up to
the site and then next time when we're
going to serve a page or iPod to this
particular type of user we'll know what
to do mmm so it's generally the idea and
this is you know not unique to eBay this
is a general idea across the industry
we're sort of closing that loop if
learning from what users have done and
directly making the site adapt due to
what the users have done in the past and
that worked for them that's better in
the past hmm okay strategy number four I
guess the most important aspect of
distributed system design at least
everything can fail independent of other
things the whole system goes down or not
parts can fail so why don't you talk
about this a little bit sure yeah the
yeah the final and very important part
of distributed systems is that you know
they fail and the more systems you have
the more likely I mean if a given
percentage of time a unit is down yeah
the more you're gonna have more units or
going to go down that's obvious so
essentially the idea is to build systems
to be tolerant of failure and to try to
continue moving as far and as fast as
they can even when other parts of this
other parts of the system or other
components that they depend on are down
so we try to we assume that every
operation will fail every resource will
be unavailable we assume you know we
make all we make all those assumptions
as part of the program in Sderot we of
course want to detect failure as quickly
as possible we want to recover from
failure as particular as quickly as
possible and while that failure is going
along we want to do as much as we
possibly can degrade gracefully degrade
gracefully exactly right
so the sort of patterns that we have
here are a sort of failure detection
pattern which I'll talk about
something that I call rollback which is
essentially undoing the operations and
then graceful degradation of the
experience so in terms of failure
detection one of the things we learned
early on at eBay is the need to have a
central application logging system that
allows our operations team and
development team for that matter to
monitor the health of the infrastructure
so every application server and piece of
infrastructure is constantly sending
events over a multicast message bus and
those we have a whole set of listeners
which are listening to various slices of
those events and aggregating them in
various ways sending of them sending
alerts and so on so it's the only way a
large-scale system can really work is by
having having some kind of monitoring
that's constantly happening and and as
available for the people who can do
something about it to to know in terms
of rollback two of the things that have
been really useful sort of two simple
approaches that we've taken I've been
very useful for us one is in the area of
code deployment and the other is in the
area of feature deployment and the fact
that they're separate from one another
which I'll talk about in this yeah so
the general rollback idea is you never
make any changes to the site that you
can't undo so it's not about rolling
back data in transactions or the non
transactions you have it's actually
about rolling back updates to the system
that's right yeah so rollback as applied
to large-scale updates the system as
distinct from a transactional rollback
yes thanks for thanks for clarifying
that's very good
so again the philosophy is that there's
no single change that we can make to the
system that can't be undone and that has
very severe implications for application
developer particularly for a schema
development right right because what
like you liked you hinted about if we
just think about it in terms of the
database what that means is that I can't
make any changes to the database schema
that I can't undo I can't make any date
changes to the the if you like interface
to the data that can't be undone
there's always needs to be backward
compatibility for data as well as
for interface so that actually gives us
a lot of challenges but because we roll
the site and we make updates to the site
every two weeks we've essentially forced
to to do this kind of thing you're
always operating different versions of
the same things in parallel yes almost
at almost at any given moment there are
almost surely multiple versions of at
least one component in flight right
because it takes us because for
thousands of application servers it
takes us serious time to be able to go
through and update all those things and
of course as with anything else things
fail so you need to be able to roll out
and roll back so so when we do cold
deployment for a particular two-week
iteration which we call a train for
historical reasons for a given train we
have what's called a rollout plan and
each feature that's on that train has
its individual rollout plan I need to
make modifications to this part of the
infrastructure this database I need to
make changes to this pool of application
servers and also to this one so we have
a individual roll out plans for features
and we roll them all up to a grand one
take what's called the transitive
closure of all the individual
dependencies of those individual rollout
plans and that's the master rollout plan
for the for the site and then we exit
and then we have automated tools that
execute that rollout plan in I was gonna
say dependency order it's actually
reverse dependency order starting with
the starting with the leaves and debris
and living backup automated tools that
do the rollout and then audit and then
if there are issues that we detect we
can automatically rollback and put
things back in the in the same place in
an automated way and you do that in the
dependency also you can have the leaves
still running but the stuff that depends
on the leaves if that cost the problem
is just remove that exactly right yeah
so we can move forward and we can
traverse up or down if you think of a
dependency tree you know if you're
traversing up or down yeah exactly hill
so that's four that's four code
deployment and then for feature
deployment every feature that we were
every significant feature that we roll
out has an on or off state so what that
means is that for any kind of reason
operational reasons business reasons
whatever we can turn on and off
feature with some sense a flip of a
button and that's much faster than doing
code rolls as you might imagine because
it's driven by a central configuration
which sort of everybody subscribes to so
that allows us to that actually allows
us to do several things one is that
decouples the code deployment from the
feature deployment it means we can roll
out code that's essentially off which we
do all the time and then we can turn it
on at some particular moment either
because we've announced we're gonna make
some pricing changes at X date and we
can turn them on at a date or because
the feature isn't working well
business-wise whatever wise and we can
turn it off it also allows us to unroll
some of those code dependencies which
can become circular right so uh changes
on this particular train you know
changes to this change of the selling
pool requires this change to the finding
pool first but there's this change to
the finding pool that requires this
other change to the certain to this
selling pool first you can unroll those
dependencies by rolling all the code out
with various flavors of on off of the
feature yep and that allows you to to
deal with that it reminds me of another
very old thing I know it by the name of
runlevels so if you want to start up a
system when you have dependencies going
around you choose to start it up to some
level where it's maybe still pass it but
everything is there and then you start
up the next level it's kind of similar
yeah I never thought about it that way
but that's absolutely right we yeah I
guess this is someone that's a that's a
great analogy I think this takes us a
little bit one step further because
instead of there's not there aren't
states of the system as a whole right
there are states of individual parts of
the system yes and and what's what what
we've ended up with is a situation where
application developers sort of check for
the availability of resources as you
would imagine they would or deal with
the unavailability of resources but they
also can check for the availability of
features in that same way and that and
sort of a similar metaphor and both of
those things and in fact and and and in
some sense from the perspective of the
code it almost doesn't matter right
either
this feature if this feature is down or
this resource is down
I don't do accent I don't care about
which why should I yeah exactly yeah
that's actually interesting yeah there's
a little bit like reflection so you have
the system knows about its own
configuration or state in the term in
terms of update inversion and then you
can react on that explicitly yeah
exactly right it's one of these things
where it shows that trying to make
things transparent application
developers really doesn't work in big
systems right also a very insightful
comment yes there a lot there are lots
of ways to say this Joel suppose Spolsky
talks about it as leaky abstractions
yeah that's a wonderful way of saying it
but yes there there are fundamental
what's the way to say it crisply the
availability state of the system is a
leaky abstraction and there's no way
around it right it's you cannot abstract
you cannot abstract the developer from
the fact that resources cannot be there
right or features cannot be there about
it that's a fundamental part of the
system and the more you try to hide that
from the developers to actually the more
complex it in make yeah because
somewhere someone's got to be available
to be aware of that
availability state and if it's not the
developer then who right yeah the magic
framework guys well Matt that's the
scary part the magic framework which
would need outrageous numbers of rules
and that's just a nut you know so in
some sense to keep it simple we make it
obvious and transparent mmm-hmm okay I
think this was the the main the main
thing Randy thank you very much for
being on the show I think this was very
interesting and well thanks thank you
very much I enjoyed
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website and
SE - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the SU radio team
by on the website or you can advertise
for su radio for example by clicking on
the Digg reddit delicious and slash dog
buttons to contact the team leaves an
email to team and SI radio net or if
it's specific to an episode please use
the comments facility on the website so
other people can read and react to your
comments this episode of software
engineering radio as well as all other
episodes are licensed under Creative
Commons license please see the website
for details thanks to Charlie crowd and
the pot safe music Network for the music
used in this show the song is called
Vegas hard rock shuffle
[Music]